<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The end of the perfect man A sermon preached at the buriall of the right Honourable Sir Robert Spencer Knight Baron Spencer of Wormeleighton, Novemb. 6. 1627. in Braynton Church in Northamptonshire, by Richard Parre Bachelour in Divinity, and late fellow of Brasen-nose Colledge in Oxford, now rector of Ladbrook in Warwickshire.</title>
            <author>Parr, Richard, 1591 or 2-1644.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09035</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19323</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114075</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849303</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849303</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14443</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09035)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14443)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1148:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The end of the perfect man A sermon preached at the buriall of the right Honourable Sir Robert Spencer Knight Baron Spencer of Wormeleighton, Novemb. 6. 1627. in Braynton Church in Northamptonshire, by Richard Parre Bachelour in Divinity, and late fellow of Brasen-nose Colledge in Oxford, now rector of Ladbrook in Warwickshire.</title>
                  <author>Parr, Richard, 1591 or 2-1644.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 29, [7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Turner, printer to the famous Vniversitie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. Dom. 1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With three final leaves of verse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spencer, Robert Spencer, --  Baron, 1570-1627 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14443:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14443:1"/>
            <p>THE END OF THE PERFECT MAN.</p>
            <p>A <hi>SERMON PREACHED AT the Buriall of the right Honourable Sir</hi> ROBERT SPENCER Knight Baron SPENCER of <hi>Wormeleighton, Novemb.</hi> 6. 1627. in <hi>Braynton Church in Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thamptonſhire,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> RICHARD PARRE Bachelour in Divinity, and late Fellow of Braſen-noſe Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Oxford, now Rector of <hi>Ladbr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>k</hi> in Warwickſhire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by WILLIAM TVRNER Printer to the famous Vniverſitie. <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1628.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14443:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14443:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> WILLIAM SPENCER, Knight of the Bathe, Baron of <hi>Wormeleighton.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable and my very good Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Ouchſafe to accept that which was both concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and brought forth at Your Lordſhips <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund;</hi> you haue giuen it a being, it now craues your protection; and the rather becauſe it brings you at once a <hi>teſtimony</hi> both of my <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>weakeneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Worth</hi> of our late noble Lord, Your worthy Father (now with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> deſerued, (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe) a farre more learned <hi>Pen,</hi> though had not neede of any: t'is the Priviledge of <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> to bee their owne <hi>Pannegyriſts, —habent opera ſuam lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guam</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Cyprian</hi>) <hi>&amp; ſuam facundiam tacente linguâ,</hi>—they haue not onely tongues of their owne, but eloquence, and in a powerfull ſilence proclaime themſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14443:3"/>'Tis therefore a ſuperfluous labour to endeauour to preſerue his memorie in theſe poore paper monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, who ſtill liues in thoſe walking <hi>images</hi> of Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, his religious and hopefull <hi>Children;</hi> ſtill liues in the ſad hearts of the poore and naked, whom his <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi> hath ſo often fed, and cloathed: in that neglected vertue of <hi>Hoſpitalitie,</hi> (for juſtly may it preſerue that <hi>Name</hi> into <hi>eternitie</hi> by which it ſelfe liues; which in this cold <hi>dotage</hi> of the decrepit <hi>World,</hi> and perpetuall froſt of <hi>Charitie,</hi> would be benumm'd or ſtaru'd, were it not entertain'd and cheriſh'd by that honourable Name of <hi>Spencer</hi> and ſome few others:) but in this Your Honour will ſatisfie the world, who beleeues You as truely to ſucceed Him in his vertues, as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions; and in his pious and religious <hi>Examples,</hi> which euer ſurviue their <hi>Authors</hi> Funerals, they haue a life of their owne, or rather an immortality, by which they not onely continue vnto poſterity, but powerfully perſwade to imitation.</p>
            <p>But ſince it hath pleaſed the dead to appoint a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and the liuing to make choiſe of my ſelfe (the moſt vnworthy of Gods Miniſters, none being more conſcious of his owne defects, none more willing to ſerue this Honourable Family according to his weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) I haue ſtudied to fit my Sermon, to his Funerals. He did not affect <hi>Pompam funeris,</hi> as <hi>Hierome</hi> ſpeakes <hi>ad Paulam</hi> vpon the death of <hi>Blaeſilla:</hi> nor I <hi>Pompam Sermonis;</hi> here's no Rhetoricke vſ'd to moue the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and affections, which are the ſtoppes and fretts of the Soule, to bee fingred by the Art of a powerfull Oratour: I know the times wee liue in to be criticall
<pb facs="tcp:14443:3"/>and touchy, and that our Funeralliſts frequently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to teach <hi>ſorrow</hi> to be eloquent, an age where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in an intemperate <hi>curioſity</hi> of ſtyle is become not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>humour,</hi> but a <hi>diſeaſe;</hi> for my part I haue choſen (in a pious obſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of that plaineſſe he required) rather to ſatisfye <hi>the deſire of the dead, then the curioſitie of the liuing;</hi> and therefore I doe not (as the olde <hi>Romanes</hi> vſed) <hi>laudare defunctum pro rostris</hi> (to ſpeake with <hi>Suetonius</hi> in his <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Shindleru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>) nor haue I painted his Sepulchre (like thoſe auncient <hi>Iewes;</hi>) no, I appeale vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world if I may not juſtly take vp that of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, testimonium veritati praebeo, non affectioni.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any accuſe this poore <hi>Peece,</hi> as <hi>Lucilius</hi> did the writings of <hi>Fabianus Papirius;</hi> for to plaine, I muſt borrow that <hi>Apologie</hi> which <hi>Seneca</hi> made for him, <hi>mores ego, non verba compoſui, &amp; animis ſcripſi illa, non auribus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca ep. <hi>100.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>That diuine Moraliſt commaunds his yong <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> that he ſhould euer ſuppoſe <hi>Cato</hi> or ſome of the ſtricter Stoickes, a beholder of all his actions,<note place="margin">Sen. ep. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the conceite of ſuch an awfull preſence, a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient direction: Your Honour needes goe no further then the happy memory of your bleſſed Father ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for direction or patterne. Suppoſe you him beſpeaking his Children as <hi>Valerius Corvinus</hi> did his Souldiers, <hi>Facta mea vos imitari vellem, nec diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam modò, ſed exemplum:</hi> take out the Lecture, and goe on (great Lord) in thoſe vertuous and pious courſes hee hath trode before you, and <hi>that</hi> God, with whom hee now raignes in glory, proſper and protect you in all your actions, guide and direct you
<pb facs="tcp:14443:4"/>in all your wayes, crowne you with the bleſſing of peace heere, and with a Crowne of glory hereafter: this ſhall euer bee the prayer of him who is, and profeſſeth ſtill to continue</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours in all humble duty and obſervance <hi>RICHARD PARRE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:14443:4"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the great wiſedome and care of our Honourable and religious Lord, now tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated from Earth to Heauen,<note n="a" place="margin">Made about three yeares before his death.</note> in his laſt Will and Teſtament, to giue directions in ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall paſſages vnto vs, who are the Actours in this laſt Sceane, of his decent and Chriſtian Burialls.</p>
            <p>Firſt for his bleſſed ſoule, that he voluntarily reſignes and bequeathes into the mighty hands of GOD his Creatour; into the gracious armes of GOD the Sonne, his Redeemer; and into the comfortable fellowſhip of GOD the Holy-Ghoſt his ſanctifyer: Three perſons, but one GOD, bleſſed for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uer.</p>
            <p>His bleſſed ſoule thus bequeathed to be admitted into the Congregation of the ſacred Trinity; into thoſe celeſtiall and euerlaſting habitations. Then hee commends the care and charge of his body to his ſurviuers with theſe enſuing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections in many circumſtances.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the <hi>Vbi</hi> or place, where it ſhould reſt, Secondly, for the manner <hi>(How)</hi> it ſhould bee brought to its place of reſt: And then, hee directs vs in this ſacred buſineſſe, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, I meane, the preaching of this Sermon.</p>
            <p>For the firſt circumſtance, the <hi>Vbi,</hi> or place of reſt, it is in the wombe of this holy ground;<note n="b" place="margin">Braynton Church in Northampton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire.</note> and more punctually, in that honourable and rich Monument with his elect Lady, &amp; beloued Wife; whoſe Chriſtian death &amp; diſſolution divided their bodies, not their ſoules:<note n="c" place="margin">He liued <hi>a</hi> Widovver 30 yeares.</note> witneſſe thoſe many yeares he hath ſpent as a mourner of her Funerals; witneſſe that indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduall Monument for them both, to teſtifie to the world, that happie vnion, of which, neither life, nor death could cauſe a diſiunction. Thus did the ſparke of his neuer-dying loue, guided by a diuine providence, kindle and inflame his heart with a deſire, not only of dying in the ſame bedde on
<pb facs="tcp:14443:5"/>earth, but alſo of lying in the ſame bed vnder earth: where they might dwell together againe, as in a houſe of ſafety and peace, vntill they riſe jointly to a joyfull and glorious reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            <p>And as we are thus confin'd to the <hi>Vbi,</hi> or place of reſt: ſo are we reſtrained in the manner <hi>(How)</hi> he would be brought thither, not in the pompous traine of Heraulds, and glorious Enſignes, nor in dumbe ceremonies, and ſuperfluous ſhewes, but in a decent &amp; Chriſtian manner, without pompe<note n="d" place="margin">Theſe are the vvords of the Will.</note> or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluitie.</p>
            <p>And as we are thus confin'd in one Circumſtance, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd in another: ſo are we preſcrib'd in the third place for the preaching of this <hi>Sermon,</hi> in the face of this Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whilſt he wils a <hi>Sermon,</hi> not a Panegyrick cloath'd in the colours of Rhetoricke, nor yet a Funerall Oration, to blazen his Honours, to hyperbolize in his praiſes, or to draw a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious line of Progenitours. No. <hi>Mallet precibus in coelum ferri, quàm plauſibus;</hi> as his ſoule went vp to Heauen in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: ſo he had rather his body ſhould bee entomb'd in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, then in vniuſt and ouer-praiſing. Therefore he wills a Sermon for the advancing of Gods glory, a Sermon for the inſtruction of his Children, and friends in the feare of God, and to ſtirre them vp to<note n="e" place="margin">Theſe are the vvords of the Will.</note> liue wel, and dye well: which by the grace of God we ſhall doe, out of the</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14443:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>37. Pſal. at the 37. Verſ.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Marke the perfect man, and behold the vpright, for the end of that man is peace.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Inis coronat opus:</hi> It is the end that crowns the worke or action, &amp; not that alone, but truely diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: paſſe by the houſe of God a little, and walke vpon the ſtage of the world, there marke and behold the promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous actions of all perſons, &amp; wee ſhall finde little diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt <hi>Ethiopians</hi> and true <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> betwixt true Chriſtians, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit formaliſts, betwixt him that offers ſweete incenſe in the Church of God, &amp; him that ſacrificeth bloud in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels Chappell; Looke vpon <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abell</hi> for the outward action, both are ſacrificing: Looke vpon <hi>Eſau</hi> &amp; <hi>Hezechia,</hi> both are weeping: Looke vpon <hi>Achab</hi> and <hi>Mordecai,</hi> both are in ſackcloath mourning: Looke vpon <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Dauid,</hi> both are confeſſing: in a word look vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the righteous &amp; the wicked, both for a time (perhaps) are like greene bay-trees, flowriſhing: but marke the end, that crownes the action,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14443:6"/>that, diſtinguiſheth the perſon; The end of the vngodly is, what?<note place="margin">2 Verſ. 39.</note> 
               <hi>Hee ſhall bee rooted out at the laſt:</hi> but for the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vpright man his end is crowned with the bleſſing of <hi>Peace. Marke the perfect man, and behold the vpright, for the end of that man is peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The parts are 3.
<list>
                  <item>1. An iniunction, <hi>Marke and behold.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The obiect or perſon, <hi>the perfect man and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right man.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The motiue, or reaſon, <hi>for the end of that man is peace.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Reſolue theſe 3. partes into theſe 3. <hi>Queries:</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, what this perfect man is, or how farre man in this life is capable of perfection?</p>
            <p>Secondly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> What the vpright, or juſt man is for our imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation?</p>
            <p>Thirdly &amp; laſtly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> what it is to end in peace for our great comfort and conſolation?</p>
            <p>Wee beginne with the firſt Querie, what <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man is; or how farre a man in this life is capable of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection? For the reſoluing of this Querie,<note place="margin">part. 1.</note> in the firſt place, the <hi>Romane</hi> Doctours diſtinguiſh thus.<note n="b" place="margin">Perfectio a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia eſt praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ac meriti, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia conſilij &amp; ſupererogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis. vi. Aquin: 2.2. quae 184. Art. 2. &amp; 3.</note> There's a perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of precept and merit, and a perfection of Counſell, and ſupererogation; the perfection of precept and merit, they determine to bee <hi>in omnibus iuſtificatis, &amp; ſaluatis;</hi> but the perfection of counſell and ſupererogation agrees onely to ſome which aſpire higher, not onely to ſaue themſelues, but others, as monaſticall votaries. Surely this is the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of men, of whom Saint <hi>Auguſt.</hi> complaines, <hi>Sunt quidam inflati,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de vcibis Apoſt. ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rm. 29.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there are ſome like veſſells blowne vp with wind, fill'd with a haughty ſpirit, not ſolidely great, but ſwoll'n with the ſickeneſſe of pride, who dare bee bold to ſay, that ſome men are without ſinne, whereas there owne <hi>Caietans</hi> rule is moſt Catholicke: <hi>damnatum eſt pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, non extinctum:</hi> Sinne is condemn'd in ſome, in none extinguiſht. And as Saint <hi>Auguſt:</hi> brands ſuch men with the ſpirit of haughtines, and pride: ſo doth Saint <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14443:6"/>bequeath vnto them a miſerable woe,<note n="a" place="margin">S. Bern. ſerm. contra vitium ingrati.</note> 
               <hi>Vae generationi huic miſerae,</hi> woe to this miſerable generation, to whom their owne inſufficiencie ſeemes moſt ſufficient. Would but the indulgent <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> learne from theſe auncient Fathers, they would not interpret our Sauiours <hi>(vade,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.21.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; vende)</hi> of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection both of merit &amp; ſupererogation: both which kinds of perfection diſtilled from Roman braines, wee of the Church of reformation deny and reiect, diſtinguiſhing of perfection, thus. The perfection which in ſacred Scriptures, and auncient Fathers, is attributed to holy men of God for their righteouſneſſe, and good workes is either
<list>
                  <item>Extrinſecall,<note n="b" place="margin">Vid. Zanch. tom. 6. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ment. in cp. ad Phil. c. 3. v. 15.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>or Intrinſecall.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Perfection Extrinſecall, adventitious, or by way of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donation, is, when that which is imperfect in vs, is freely pardon'd by God, for Chriſts ſake, according to that of S. <hi>Aug:</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">S. Aug. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Retr. cap. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Omnia Dei mandata facta deputantur,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Aug. 19. de ciu. Dei. c. 27.</note> 
               <hi>quando id qd non fit ignoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ur:</hi> all the commandements of God, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted perform'd, or done, when that is freely forgiuen which is vndone: And againe, ſuch is our righteouſneſſe or perfection in this life, that it conſiſts <hi>in remiſſione peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum potius quám in perfectione virtutum:</hi> rather in the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes, then in the perfection of vertues.</p>
            <p>Secondly Intrinſeccall perfection, or perfection by way of inheſion, is either abſolute, which is nothing elſe, but ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity or ſimplicity of heart, oppoſ'd to hypocriſie, or dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dealing with God; in which ſenſe <hi>Iob</hi> is ſaid (<hi>Chap.</hi> 1.1.) to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a perfect man: or elſe it is comparatiue in a certaine reſpect, or by way of compariſon with others, &amp; ſo <hi>Noah</hi> is ſaid to bee perfect: (<hi>Gen.</hi> 6.9.) but with this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition <hi>(in generationibus ſuis)</hi> that is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.9.</note> he was very righteous and perfect in reſpect of others, that liued in thoſe lewd, &amp; godleſſe times; ſo Saint <hi>Paul</hi> elegantly expreſſeth himſelfe. <hi>Wee ſpeake wiſedome amongſt thoſe that are perfect.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7. i. amongſt them which haue a greater meaſure of grace,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7.</note> &amp; knowledge then moſt of you haue: for otherwiſe, if wee ſpeake of abſolute perfection, hee is abſolutely againſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14443:7"/>it,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.12.</note> and confeſſeth of himſelfe,<note n="a" place="margin">S. Aug. in Pſ. 38.</note> that he had not attained vnto it, (<hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12.) And <hi>Quis ſibi arrogare id audeat, quod Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus ipſe fatetur ſe non comprehendiſſe?</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">S. Bernard in Cant. ſerm. 49.</note> S. <hi>Bern. ſuper Cant. ſerm.</hi> 50. And as for that ſeeming contradiction raiſ'd out of the 15. verſe. implying in himſelfe,<note n="c" place="margin">Auguſt. de tempore ſerm. 49.</note> and exhorting others to Perfection, Saint <hi>Auguſt,</hi> wipes it away with this ſhort diſtinction. S. <hi>Paul</hi> was perfect <hi>ſecundum intentionem, non ſecundum preuentione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> perfect, in regard of intention, &amp; pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, not in regard of prouention, and obeying his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: And Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> is no leſſe plaine, &amp; peremptorie in the caſe, <hi>Magnum illud electionis vas perfectum ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuit, profectum fatetur.</hi> That great choſen veſſell of election graunts profection, that is, a going forward, but denies perfection. Well then doth Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> conclude the point. <hi>Perfectio hominis in hâc vit â eſt, inveniſſe, ſe non eſſe perfectum.</hi> The perfection of man in this life is, to finde, and acknowledge himſelfe not to bee perfect.<note n="*" place="margin">How the Law is poſſible or im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſſible to bee <hi>perfectly</hi> fulfil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led. See the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſarts Appeale by <hi>Thom. Mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ton, D.</hi> of Di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uinity, and new Lor Biſhop of <hi>Couentry</hi> &amp; <hi>Lichfield. lib. 5. ca: 12. ſect 2.</hi>
               </note> And as for the cloud of witneſſes which ſcemes to riſe vppe againſt this trueth in ſacred Scriptures:<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 17.1. Deut 18.13. Matth. 5: 48. 2: Cor. 13.11. Epheſ. 1.4: 5: 27. 1: P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t: 1: 15:</note> Saint <hi>Auguſt:</hi> ſupplies vs with ſeuerall anſwers which hee reduceth to theſe ſeuerall heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt, hee anſwereth, that ſome of theſe places are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations, and admonitions, whereby wee are ſtirred vppe ſo to runne the race which is ſet before vs,<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Aug: lib: de iuſtitia Chriſti contra Coeleſt tom: 7: S. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uguſtins</hi> foure wayes of anſwering ſuch Scriptures which ſeeme to plead for an abſolute ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dience to Gods will &amp; Commandemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</note> that wee faint not, though wee cannot attaine vnto it; for in lawes and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions that is not alwayes required. <hi>Vt tantum praeſtari poſſit quantum ſuadetur:</hi> that ſo much ſhould bee perform'd by vs, as is enioyn'd to vs: but in them is ſhewed vnto vs <hi>Quouſque conari oportet:</hi> how carneſtly wee ought to ſtriue and follow hard toward the marke for the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, hee anſwers, that many of theſe places doe ſhew vnto vs, not what, we (now) are, but what we ſhall be at the end of our pilgrimage, for then, wee ſhall bee perfect when we arriue at that hauen whither wee bend our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian courſe, or race.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:14443:7"/>3 Thirdly, when the Scripture mentions men that are perfect, and immaculate, we are to vnderſtand by them ſuch men, who haue not defil'd their garments, or polluted their conſciences, with groſſe and damnable enormities; in this ſenſe, many of the Saintes of God are ſaid to be perfect, not that they are without ſinne, (which is impoſſible) but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, it raignes not in their mortall bodies, or becauſe they haue not wallow'd with the ſwine in the mire, but kept themſelues vnſpotted of the world.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Laſtly, the Saintes of God are ſaid to bee perfect, and without blame, and reproofe; nay, innocent &amp; bleſſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their ſinnes are not imputed vnto them, but freely forgiuen in, and for Chriſt: for ſo it runnes. <hi>Bleſſed is the man whoſe wickedneſſe is forgiuen, and vnto whom the Lord imputeth no ſinne. Pſal,</hi> 32.1.<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.1: a <hi>S:</hi> Aug. in Loc:</note> Which ſweete paſſage Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> makes to excell all others read vnto vs in the Church militant, for the fitting, and preparing of a dying ſoule for the Church triumphant: and good reaſon for it; for, what the Lord forgiues, who can require? what he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puteth not, who ſhall bring it out, againſt vs, to iudgement? Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods choſen?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33.</note> 'tis God that iuſtifieth: &amp; how? not only by taking our vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe from vs, but by giuing vs his own righteouſnes, <hi>for Chriſt Ieſus is made vnto vs wiſedome and righteouſneſſe.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1 30. This righteouſneſſe being ours by the free gift &amp; imputation of God, is not now, <hi>alienaſed noſtra iuſtitia.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30.</note> But not to looſe the point on foot, i. how farre a man in this life is capable of perfection: There is (yee know) a perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of partes, and a perfection of degrees:<note place="margin">Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio Parti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duum.</note> The former is when a man hath reſpect to all the Commaundements of God, not allowing himſelfe in the breach of any of them: the latter perfection, is, when a man performes all exactly, as the Law in rigour requires; hee that is perfect the firſt way may be reſembled to a weake and feeble child, that hath all the integrall, &amp; perfect parts of a man, but not perfectly, or (to ſpeake with the Logicians) <hi>integralitèr,</hi> integrally;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14443:8"/>againe, hee that is perfect the latter way, may bee reſembled to a ſtrong growne-man that hath all his partes in perfect vigour. To apply then, we may be perfect the firſt way (i.) a man may haue perfection of partes,<note place="margin">How a man in this life may bee ſaid to be perfect ſaid to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> becauſe hee may loue euery good, and hate euery euill in ſome meaſure: but the ſecond way wee are not perfect, (i.) a man cannot haue a perfection of degrees, becauſe hee canne neither loue good, nor hate euill as be ſhould; the firſt kind of perfection then, wee grant; the ſecond, wee deny: neither that, as touching exact performance <hi>continually,</hi> but as touching conſtant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution <hi>habitually.</hi> Neither is this al we vnderſtand by <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,</hi> or haue to ſay for the perfect man, by whom, in a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place, wee may ſafely vnderſtand the innocent man, ſo the <hi>Septuagint</hi> reades it.<note place="margin">The innocent man.</note> 
               <hi>Cuſtodi innocentiam,</hi> keepe inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, or marke the innocent man, the man that makes a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with his eyes, and whoſe hand is not imbrued in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, the man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is as innocent,<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 31.1.</note> as a doue,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 10.16.</note> that wrongs no man, oppreſſes no man, but as much as in him lies doeth good vnto all men.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Perfecte bonus eſt, &amp; vere dicitur inſons,</l>
               <l>Nec ſibi, nec cujquam, quod noceat faciens.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſimple and plaine-dealing-man.</note>Againe, by <hi>the perfect man,</hi> wee may ſafely vnderſtand the ſimple and plaine-dealing-man, the man that is ſimple con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning euil, for ſo the vulgar reads it <hi>cuſtodi ſimplicitatem;</hi> keepe ſimplicity,<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.19.</note> or marke the ſimple and plaine-dealing-man, who in ſimplicity, and godly pureneſſe, not in fleſhly wiſedome hath had his conuerſation in the world: this ſimple man diſſembleth not betwixt God and man,<note n="d" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12.</note> neither is he in the number of thoſe, of whom the Poet complaines.</p>
            <q>Ore aliud, tacitoque aliud ſub pectore condunt.</q>
            <p>Not hee mindes the ſame thing, hee ſpeakes the ſame thing, hee doth the ſame thing, without any reſpect of perſons, though it be to his owne preiudice, or hinderance.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, by the perfect man wee may ſarely vnderſtand, the man who is, <hi>Integer vitae, ſceleriſque purus,</hi> a man of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of heart,<note place="margin">The ſincere man.</note> &amp; of a pure, and vpright conuerſation, for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14443:8"/>ſo <hi>Iunius</hi> and <hi>Tremelius</hi> read it, <hi>Obſerua integrum</hi> in the concrete, &amp; the Chaldee paraphraſe in the abſtract, <hi>Obſerua integritatem</hi> marke the integrity of the perfect man. This grace of integritie of the heart, and inward affections is <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diametro</hi> oppoſ'd to hypocriſie, diſſimulation or double dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with God: God loues trueth in the inward affections: and if God loue it, wee muſt loue it: and why? becauſe, in a conformity with God, ſtands mans felicitie: In this inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of heart and trueth in the inward affections are two things; holineſſe and ſincerity, oppoſite to ſinne, and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crine: wee muſt write holineſſe vnto the Lord, or elſe wee ſhall neuer ſee God: we muſt ſeaſon all our actions with the grace of Sincerity elſe wee ſhall neuer pleaſe him: but the ſpeculation of theſe two graces, holineſſe and ſincerity: will be more cleare in the view of their oppoſites, finne and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peccatum</hi> ſinne, in the Schoole of God, is taught to be an exorbitancie, a ſwaruing from the rule of trueth,<note place="margin">What ſinne is.</note> a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of the law: and ſinne in the Schooles of men is taught to be <hi>mendacium,</hi> a lye, and to lye is to goe againſt the minde, or for the tongue te giue to the heart the lye; in ſhedding of blood, the hand onely lyes, or is falſe to the heart, and in a common lye, the tongue onely lyes againſt the heart: but in hypocriſie is a generall lye of the whole man: not the tongue onely, lyes to the heart, but the eye, the hand, the knee, and the foote alſo; the hand is lifted vppe to heauen, the eyes looke vp to God, the feete goe, the knees bend and bowe in the Temple of GOD, but where's the heart? doth that goe along with them? no! The heart of the couetous man. is where his treaſure is; the heart of the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious man, is, where his honour is: and the heart of a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuous man, is, where his pleaſure is, —<hi>Haec tria pro trino numine mundus habet,</hi> this is the trynitie which theſe world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings worſhip: for although their feete goe, and their knees bowe in the Temple of God, though their eyes and handes be lifted vp to heauen, yet their hearts are groueling heer
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14443:9"/>on earth; it is the pollicy of ſin to imitate ſincerity, and the guiſe of hypocriſie to follow the faſhions of integrity: the heires of darkeneſſe transforme themſelues into Angels of Light, and Baſtard Chriſtians can counterfeit perfect mens behauiours, yet thoſe heires of darkeneſſe are not children of the light, nor theſe counterfeit, true Chriſtians: and why? becauſe they come ſhort in this grace of ſincetity, or inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of heart: The painter can paint the colour of the fire, &amp; the forme of the flame thereof, but cannot paint the heate of it: right ſo, the counterfeit ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble the perfect Chriſtian in outward colours, formes &amp; faſhions, but not in his integrity of heart, or truth in the inward affections: <hi>Eſau</hi> can weepe bitterly, like <hi>Hezechia: Achab</hi> can put on ſack-cloth, like <hi>Mordecay;</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> can confeſſe in word <hi>I haue ſinned</hi> as well as <hi>Dauid:</hi> yet neither <hi>Eſau,</hi> nor <hi>Achab,</hi> nor <hi>Saul</hi> was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a perfect man: and why? becauſe none of their hearts were perfect in the ſight of the Lord; ſuch hypocrites are the greateſt enemies to the Church, and truth, yet they will ſeeke protection both from truth and Church: Soe <hi>Celſus</hi> and <hi>Antiphon</hi> writing againſt the truth, entitle their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, the booke of truth. Soe <hi>Romes</hi> Proſelites vnder the name of the Church,<note n="a" place="margin">Origen con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Celſum.</note> ouerthrow the Church: <hi>Leo</hi> tels them truly <hi>Bccleſiae nomine armamini,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Leo, ep. 83.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; contra eam dimicatis:</hi> Such men make conſcience &amp; iuſtice the greateſt martyrs in the world; the greate man in doing miſchiefe, pretendes ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, the meane man alwaies co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience: God &amp; a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence are pretended on alſides: thus making good <hi>Luthers</hi> Prouerbe,<note n="c" place="margin">Luther in 3. ad Coll.</note> 
               <hi>In nomine Domini incipit omne malum,</hi> In the name of God they Chriſten all their actions. But God is the God of truth, and loues trueth in the inward affections, therefore ſuch hypocriſie muſt needes bee an abomination vnto him, it offends him, it grieues his ſpirit, and at laſt it ſhall grieue the ſoules of them who are the authors of it, for it ſhall ſpoyle them of inward joy, and peace of conſcience here, and of eternall joy and peace in the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:14443:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>It is ſtoried of <hi>Conſtantinus,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Copronymus,</hi> that he was <hi>neque Chriſtianus, neque Iudaeus nec Paganus, ſed Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luuies quaedam impietatis,</hi> that hee was neither Chriſtian, Iewe nor Pagan, but a certaine maſſe or heape of impieties: and ſo (indeed) are all hypocrites: with the <hi>Iewes</hi> they ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Chriſt as their king, yet buffet him: they protect him with the Chriſtian, yet perſecute him with the Pagan: they are named Iſraelites, but liue like Aethiopians: they ſpeake with the voyce of <hi>Iacob,</hi> but worke with the hands of <hi>Eſau,</hi> and walke with the feete of <hi>Ioab,</hi> that any man may perceiue not by their coate, but their party-coloured con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, that they are baſtards and no Chriſtians. But leaue we theſe Hypocrites to their baſtard broode, to their vtter condemnation, to their <hi>vae, vae, vae,</hi> woe, woe, woe, in the Goſpell, &amp; come to our ſelues, whileſt condemnation falls on their pates, would we haue the ſaluation of God ſhewed on vs? then muſt we with our perfect man in the text, <hi>order our conuerſation aright,</hi> and endeauour to ſerue God in the grace of integrity, with cleane hands &amp; pure hearts, <hi>for who ſhall aſcend into the hill of the Lord?</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 24.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>euen he that hath cleane hands and a pure heart, hee ſhall receiue the bleſſing from the Lord, and righteouſneſſe from the God of his ſaluation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is there any way or meanes to know whether wee our ſelues, or others, are ſuch men of cleane hands and pure hearts? yes! <hi>Ex fructibus cognoſcetis,</hi> by their fruites yee ſhall know them: for good and godly men are like trees planted by the riuer ſide, which bring forth their fruites in due ſeaſon. I demand then? what are theſe ſeaſonable fruits?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 1.3.</note> doubtles, they are good works, &amp; thoſe good worksare of 3. ſorts: of Piety towards God, of equity towards our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, of ſobriety towards our ſelues: &amp; as the works, ſo the fruites are of 3. ſorts: by the 1. God is glorified, by the 2. our neighbour is edified, &amp; by the 3. our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firm'd in the aſſurance of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, For howſoeuer good work sare no meriting cauſes, yet they are witneſſing, effects or aſſurances of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; Make your calling &amp; election ſure:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14443:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>('tis S. <hi>Peters</hi> exhortation; <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10.</note>) but how? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by good workes, (<hi>Beza</hi> confeſſeth he ſaw two greeke Manuſcripts with thoſe expreſſe words of the text:) good works haue no place in the act of iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for by good works <hi>(cauſatiue)</hi> ſhall not man liuing be iuſtified, without good workes <hi>(con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequutiue)</hi> ſhall no man liuing bee ſaued: Oh that all diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting about good workes were turned into doing, and that euery Chriſtian would take it into his higher conſideration, that, although he is not now juſtified by good workes, yet at that great and notable day of the Lord, he ſhall be iudg'd according to his good workes. Oh that our fruitleſſe profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours would lay this cloſe to their hearts tell me what haue they to witneſſe for them, that they are Chriſtians? Their tongues and lippes ſay they are ſoe: but, what ſay their liues and workes? Looke vpon their vncleane eyes, full of adulteries and luſt: harken to their diſlolute ſpeeches, full of oathes and blaſphemies: ſee their polluted hands, imbru'd in blood and full of violence: marke their feete how nimble, and ſwift, they are to ſhed innocent blood: do not theſe abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations proclaime them to be Pagans, rather then Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians? they feede not the hungry, they cloth not the naked, they viſit not the fatherleſſe and widdowes, they keepe not themſelues vnſpotted of the world, and yet theſe men, would haue the honour to bee reputed good Chriſtians, (i.) perfect and abſolute men in all good workes. But to conclude this point or Querie, concerning the <hi>perfect man:</hi> if we tender the great honour of being reputed ſuch perfect and vpright men, then let vs bee zealous of good workes: and why? becauſe they are the fruites of our perfection, of our integritie and trueth in inward affections: nay, they are the very high waies wherein God hath ordain'd vs to walke: wee are his worke-manſhip created in Chriſt Ieſus vnto good workes, which God hath ordain'd that wee ſhould walke in them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10. Oh then let vs euen ſtriue with a holy emulation, to go one before another in good workes, and to abound in them; ye know the Apoſtles ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14443:10"/>hortation. <hi>As long as wee haue time let vs do good,</hi> and why? becauſe when all other things in this world, our pleaſures, our honours, our lands, our liuings, our parents, our friends, and whatſoeuer elſe is vnder the cope of heauen, ſhall leaue and forſake vs, yet our good deedes (euen ſo ſaith the ſpirit) our good deedes ſhall follow vs, and ſollicite for a bleſſing vpon the ſoules of all perfect men, when they returne to the chiefe ſheepheard &amp; Biſhop of their ſoules, Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; in whoſe gracious armes I leaue the perfect man,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.25.</note> and our firſt conſideration of him, and in the next place craue your patience, whileſt wee direct your thoughts and deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the contemplation of the vpright man. <hi>Behold the vpright.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marke the perfect man and behold the vpright.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the vpright or iuſt man I finde it thus diſtinguiſht to my hand: A man may be ſaid juſt 4. waies.<note place="margin">Pars. 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>2 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>3 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>4 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The firſt way of being <hi>vpright,</hi> or iuſt, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according to nature: and ſoe no man liuing was euer iuſt ſince the fall of <hi>Adam.</hi> This the Preacher proclaimes (as it were) on the houſe top, with an aſſeueration, <hi>Certè</hi> ſurely there is no man iuſt in the earth that doth good, &amp; ſinneth not<note n="a" place="margin">In our laſt tranſlation the <hi>20.</hi> verſe.</note> 
               <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.22.</p>
            <p>The ſecond way of being juſt: is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according to the opinion and iudgment of men: ſuch were <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Samuel, whoſe O xe haue I taken &amp;c. and they ſayd thou haſt not.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.</note> verſe 4.</p>
            <p>The third way of beeing iuſt, is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according to purpoſe and true endeauour, and thus Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was juſt, when hee tels vs, that hee forgets thoſe things which are behind, and reaches forth to the thinges which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.13. And as S. <hi>Paul</hi> was thus juſt in practiſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.13.</note> ſoe was hee in precept, charging euery man to giue tribute to whom tribute is due,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 17.7.</note> cuſtome to whom cuſtome &amp;c. juſt ſo the Moraliſts bring in their verdict, preſcribing the juſt man to giue <hi>ſuum cuique,</hi> that vnto euery man which of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14443:11"/>right belongs vnto him: &amp; this <hi>(ſuum)</hi> neceſſarily implies as peculiar diſtinction &amp; propertie of things: neither doth the Politicians pen alone domonſtrate this, but it is the tenour of diuine iuſtice. <hi>Achab</hi> a King may not take away the vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard of <hi>Naboth</hi> his ſubiect,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Kings</hi> 21.</note> 2. <hi>Kings.</hi> 21. this is the rule or Canon of Scripture.</p>
            <p>Where yet I finde a fourth way of being vpright or juſt, which is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by, or according to imputation. Thus <hi>Abraham</hi> was a juſt man, he beleeued and it was imputed to him for righteouſneſſe. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.3. Here is the opening of the fountaine,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.3.</note> or Ocean of Gods ouer-flowing goodneſſe, who in mercy accounts vs iuſt and righteous, in, and for the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, which is made ours this way <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by imputation: hee layd on him the iniquity of vs all: <hi>Eſay</hi> 53.6. Our God accounts our ſinne, his, and ſoe he is puniſhed as a ſinner,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 53.6.</note> and then he accounts his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ours, and ſo wee are rewarded as righteous. This is that royall exchange made betwixt Chriſt Ieſus, and all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing ſinners: he becomes a curſe for them, that they may be the <hi>heires</hi> of bleſſing through him. Thus wee ſee what the vpright man is euery way for our inſtruction. It now remaines, that we make him our owne by way of imitation: neyther is this left to our owne choyce or pleaſure,<note place="margin">Note.</note> to do, or not to do. Noe, the text inioynes it, and by way of authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty commands vs <hi>to marke the perfect man, and to behold the vpright:</hi> and the ingemination or doubling of the iniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, marke and behold, giues way and cleare paſſage to this naturall obſeruation. That it is the duty of all ſuch, as deſire to be vpright and perfect men, to propoſe to themſelues the liues and deathes of ſuch men, as patternes to encourage the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on in their Chriſtian courſe and conuerſation.</p>
            <p>We haue here no abiding city, we are Pilgrimes and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets: if we were not ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers <hi>Non hinc emigraremus</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Aug.</hi>) we ſhould not paſſe hence:<note place="margin">2 De verb. dom. ſerm. 32.</note> but hence we muſt paſſe, wil we, nil we: &amp; in this our paſſage, there are many obſtacles which may hinder vs: many allurements which may diuert
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14443:11"/>vs: it is therefore the goodneſſe and wiſedome of God, in this our pilgrimage, to leade vs by the light, and examples of <hi>perfect and vpright men: taenquám per ſtatuas Mercuriales.</hi> that in the end of our pilgrimage on earth, wee may ſafely reſt, where they doe, in the kingdome of heauen: to men of ingenuitie (much more of grace) good mens examples, and gracious carriages, are powerfull and winning meanes; thus <hi>Iſaackes</hi> gracious carriage drew <hi>Abimelechs,</hi> and his friends affections vnto him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.28.</note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.28. Thus <hi>Iacobs</hi> religious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation drew <hi>Laban,</hi> and put him vpon that earneſt ſuite, <hi>I pray thee if</hi> I <hi>haue found fauour in thine eies, tarry: Gen.</hi> 30.27. Neither is it without good ground, that God would haue perfect, &amp; vpright mens liues exemplary: for, they are powerful, not only to perſwade imitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but alſo to enforce approbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the conuicted conſciences of the gain-ſaiers: No man is ſo badde, but would conforme himſelfe to good courſes, if they croſſed not his priuate ends: and though hee ſpeake ſometimes againſt the life, yet would bee glad to die the death of the righteous. Againe, the very nature of man is more inclineable to be guided by<note n="a" place="margin">Longum iter per praecepta, breue &amp; efficax per exempla. Sence.</note> example, then precept: Though precepts, and inſtructions be more reaſonable, yet exampies preuaile ſooner, becauſe more obuious and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar. With what courage and life doe ſouldiers goe on if they behold a Commaunder ingag'd in ſome noble attempt? his valour makes them couragious, and his example is a powerfull argument to prouoke their emulation, emulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on puts them forwards to the imitation of excellent men, as wee ſee in <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Vale: Max: l. 8. ca, 15. &amp; in Plau. Apoth:</note> whom the trophees of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiades</hi> would not ſuffer to ſleepe, vntill, by his like worthy acts, he had purchaſed to himſelf a like glorious name; &amp; as it is thus in meere naturall men and Heathens: ſo ſhould it bee amongſt Chriſtians in their Chriſtian warfares. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> takes this to be a moſt winning courſe, and therefore hee cries, <hi>Bee yee followers of mee as I am of Chriſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1.</note> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. Beſides theſe motiues, there are two weighty cauſes more, why the liues and deaths of <hi>perfect and vpright men</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:14443:12"/>ſhould bee exemplarie vnto vs: the firſt is, for the glory of God; the ſecond is, for the iuſtice of God: firſt, the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of ſuch mens liues as examples to our ſelues doth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance the glorie of God, becauſe, wee ſeeing, or looking on their good workes, do thereby learne to glorifie our Father which is in heauen:</p>
            <p>Secondly, the propoſing of ſuch mens deaths, or ends, makes for Gods iuſtice: <hi>Ne Deus putetur iniquus,</hi> (it is the gloſſe vpon the place) leaſt God ſhould be thought vniuſt whileſt wee ſee the godly to ſuffer in paine, and the wicked ſurfet in pleaſure. For which very cauſe <hi>Epicurus</hi> denieth Gods prouidence, not dreaming of that great day of reckoning, wherein the Lord ſhall come with 10000 Saintes to execute iudgement vpon all ſuch men,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude.</hi> 15.</note> or, when the Lord Ieſus ſhall bee reueal'd from heauen in fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire, to execute vengeance on all men, that would not know God,<note n="d" place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7.</note> nor obey the Goſpel of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: not dreaming, that they who now ſurfet in pleaſure, ſhall one day ſuffer in paine, and flames of hell fire: if wee haue our heauen here, wee muſt haue our hell hereafter, <hi>Nemo poteſt &amp; in hâc vitâ &amp; in futurâ gaudere:</hi> if our way in this world be pleaſant and ſweete, wee ſhall not much care for our heauenly <hi>Hieruſalem</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Cui peregri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio duleis eſt, non amat patriam. S. Aug. in Pſal. 93.</note> which is aboue; it is therefore the lot of the righteous, to ſow in teares here, that they may reape in ioy hereafter: they muſt weep in this vale of teares, that they may ſing and looke vp with joy vnto thoſe hills from whence commeth ſaluation. God in ſacred writ is ſaid to wipe away all teares, and happie are they that canne ſhed them: hee is ſaid to gather, and bleſſed are they that ſcatter them; oh then let all the <hi>Epicures</hi> of the world wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low themſelues in their ſinfull pleaſures for a ſeaſon: Let all inordinate perſons put off the euill day and euen weary themſelues in the wayes of wickedneſſe, &amp; make a progreſſe in ſinue, adding thirſt vnto drunkenneſſe; but let all the Saintes and ſeruants of God runne in the wayes of <hi>vpright men,</hi> and in patience waite vntill the day ſhall come, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14443:12"/>in they ſhall ſay, verily there is a reward for the righteous, doubtleſſe there is a God that iudgeth the earth: let them (I ſay) in patience waite the Lords leaſure, and in patience runne the race that is ſet before them, runne the race of the <hi>Perfect and vpright man,</hi> leaſt their liues and deaths runne to riſe vppe in iudgement againſt them: Let them ſo runne, that they may obtain:<note n="a" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.24:</note> and what? <hi>Coronam gloriae,</hi> a crowne of glorie in one<note n="b" place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.4.</note> place: let them ſo runne, that they may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and what? <hi>Coronam vitae,</hi> a Crowne of life, in another place<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 2.10.</note>: let them ſo runne, that they may obtaine, and what? <hi>Coronam iuſtitiae,</hi> a Crown of righteouſues, in a third place<note n="d" place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</note>; All theſe Crownes, a Crowne of glorie, a Crowne of life, a Crowne of righteouſneſſe, ſhall God (for his trueth and promiſe ſake) as rewardes giue vnto them, if they propoſe, and propoſing follow in all good conſcience the liues and deaths of perfect and vpright men.</p>
            <p>Yea, but ſuch mens liues and deaths are rare examples, <note place="margin">Ob.</note> 
               <hi>non cuiuis contingit,</hi> euery man cannot attaine to ſuch perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: what then? <hi>Eſt aliquid prodire tenus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note> eſpecially to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, who accepts the will for the deede: Nay, who ſtands at the doore, and knockes, beeing more willing to come to vs, then wee to him. Yea,<note place="margin">Ob.</note> but ſuch mens liues are full of difficulties, anxieties, and dangers:<note place="margin">Sol.</note> true! but what's the iſſue? a gracious deliuerance, the bleſſing of <hi>Peace</hi> at the laſt: many are the troubles of the righteous, but the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuers them out of all. Who would haue thought, that when <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was in the dungeon, hee ſhould euer haue beene a Lord to his brethren, or a prouident Father to a whole Nation? Who would euer haue thought, that, when <hi>Iob</hi> was ſcraping his ſores on the dung-hill, hauing loſt all his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, al his cattel, all his houſes &amp; goods, he ſhould haue bin richer then euer he was? Surely, this is the Lords doing, and it is marueilous in our eyes: many were the troubles of good old <hi>Abraham,</hi> but the Lord deliuer'd him out of all: many were the troubles of good <hi>Dauid,</hi> but the Lord deliuer'd him out of all. What ſhall I ſay more? many are the troubles
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14443:13"/>of euery <hi>perfect and vpright man,</hi> but the Lord deliuers him out of all: all theſe troubles ſhall bring him <hi>peace</hi> at the laſt, <hi>for the end of that man is peace,</hi> our laſt querie or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: <hi>Marke the perfect man, and behold the vpright, for the end of that man is Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Schooles in their laborinths doe winde and turne <hi>peace</hi> by many diſtinctions,<note place="margin">Pars 3. Aquinas, 22. q. 29. acric. 1.</note> and queries: <hi>Aquinas</hi> in foure Articles, makes 4 queries of <hi>Peace.</hi> 1. Whether it be the ſelf ſame thing with concord. Secondly, whether <hi>Peace</hi> bee an effect of charity? Thirdly, whether <hi>Peace</hi> bee deſired of all? And laſtly, whether <hi>Peace</hi> be a vertue? For the firſt querie, the verdict is brought in negatiue; <hi>Peace</hi> is not the ſame with Concord, for there may bee a concord amongſt the wicked; <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Leui</hi> were <hi>fratres in malo,</hi> brethren in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill: Amongſt the wicked then,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.5.</note> there may be concord, <hi>but there is no peace to the wicked</hi> (ſaith my God) <hi>Eſay</hi> 48.22. The reſt of the queries concerning <hi>peace</hi> will not bee ſo caſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolu'd,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 48.22.</note> therefore I muſt referre him that deſires a farther in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, vnto <hi>Aquinas</hi> 22. <hi>quaſt.</hi> 29. <hi>art.</hi> 2.3.4. where alſo hee thus diſtinguiſheth of <hi>Peace;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pax Perfecta, Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecta.</note> There is a <hi>peace</hi> which is perfect, and a <hi>peace</hi> which is imperfect: The perfect <hi>peace</hi> conſiſts in the fruition of the chiefeſt good, and is the vlti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate end of the reaſonable creature, according to that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Qui poſuit tuos ſines pacem,</hi> and this kind of <hi>peace</hi> is not to bee had but in the world to come. The imperfect peace is that which may be had in this world &amp; principally ſtands and reſts in the contemplation of God and his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, yet not without ſome repugnancies both within, and without, which diſturbe this <hi>peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hugo de Sancto Victore</hi> tells vs of foure kindes of <hi>peace, Duas dat mundus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hugo de San: Vict. annotat. elucida: in Pſal. 62. &amp; 84.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; duas dat Deus;</hi> The world giues two, and God two: The firſt Peace which the world giues, is, the quiet enioying of temporall thinges: The ſecond is, the health, or ſafety of our bodies: The firſt Peace that God giues, is, the ſweete tranquility of the minde; &amp; the ſecond is, that great delight and ioy which wee take in the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of God; <hi>That</hi> is in man, <hi>This</hi> aboue man: Againe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14443:13"/>there is <hi>Pax temporis,</hi> which is nothing elſe but a temporall tranquillity: Secondly, there is <hi>Pax pectoris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dionyſ. Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> lib. de pace.</note> which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but a reſt, or peace of the minde, according to that of our Sauiour, <hi>Theſe thinges haue I ſpoken vnto you, that in me yee might haue peace:</hi> Laſtly, there is <hi>Pax aeternitatis,</hi> which conſiſts in the ioyes of heauen, which God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for thoſe that loue him. All theſe ioyes howſoeuer multiplied in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, yet they aime at an end <hi>in pace:</hi> For, <hi>finis ciuitatis huius</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſt:</hi>) the end of the Saintes of God in the citty of God, is, either Peace in eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, or eternall life in Peace.</p>
            <p>But all this while we haue not determin'd the Querie in the text, what it is to end, or die in peace: neither canne wee well conclude that, before wee haue taken ſpeciall notice of two materiall circumſtances.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Firſt, of the neceſſity of dying.</item>
               <item>2 Secondly, of the vniuerſality of dying. There is Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute-law for both, which no mortall canne repeale,<note place="margin">Heb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Statu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt omnibus,</hi> it is appointed that all muſt once die: <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum eſt,</hi> there's the neceſſity, <hi>omnibus,</hi> there's the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For the neceſſity of dying, as ſure as wee are borne to liue, ſo ſure are we borne to die: <hi>Naſci &amp; denaſci ordorerum eſt,</hi> to bee borne, and to die, is the order and courſe of all thinges: Many men haue liu'd long, long enioyed the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of length of dayes, but yet thoſe dayes haue not out-li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved death: no! The ſame ſpirit of trueth which tells vs that <hi>Adam</hi> liu'd ſo many hundred yeares, tels vs alſo,<note place="margin">Gen <hi>5.5.</hi>
               </note> that hee (dyed.) <hi>Enos</hi> liu'd ſo many, and hee (died:) <hi>Cainan</hi> ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and (died:) <hi>Methuſalem</hi> ſo many, and (died:) Theſe men liu'd many daies, and months, and yeares, nay, hundreds of yeares, yet theſe many dayes, months, yeares, and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of yeares, could not out-date death, could not free them from the curſe of a <hi>morte morieris,</hi> thou ſhalt die the death. <hi>Hoc ſingulis additur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. <hi>2.17.</hi>
               </note> (The note which ſome inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters, giue on this place is worth the taking vp:) <hi>Vt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deas
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14443:14"/>efficacem fuiſſe ſententiam mortis á Deo latam in Adamum peccatum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caluinus. Cornel: á La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pide, <hi>with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> in 5, Geneſeus.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; poſteros eius:</hi> (died) is added to euery one, that wee may ſee, the power and efficacie of that doome &amp; ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, which God gaue on <hi>Adam</hi> ſinning, and on all the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full brood of <hi>Adam,</hi> which ſtill lie ſoaking in the ſame lees of corruption, and ſo much the <hi>Hebrew</hi> phraſe imports, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>moriendo morieris:</hi> i. <hi>thou ſhalt ſurely die:</hi> I need not to trauell farre for any more examples: onely caſt your eyes <hi>on this ſad ſpectacle of mortality,</hi> and then conclude of a neceſſitie: for if art or learned induſtry of Phyſicke could haue continued him, if ſtrength of man could haue deliuer'd him, if wiſedome could haue ſau'd him, if wealth of man could haue ranſom'd him; deaths arreſt had neuer attach't him, deaths ſerjeant had neuer impriſon'd him; if greatnes of eſtate, if gifts of minde, if chaſteneſſe of life, if ſobernes in diet, if wiſhes of men, if prayers of the Church could haue preuail'd for him, if any thing could haue giuen any advantage againſt death, darkeneſſe and blackeneſſe had not at this time couer'd him.</p>
            <p>And as nothing canne repeale that ſtatute enacted in the court of heauen for the neceſſity of dying, ſo nothing canne alter the decree for the vniuerſality of dying: <hi>Statutum eſt omnibus,</hi> all muſt die: <hi>All fleſh is graſſe, and all the glorie of man as the flowre of the field, Eſay,</hi> 40.6. Loe the condition of all,<note place="margin">Eſay. <hi>40.6.</hi>
               </note> as well great ones, as meane ones, their glorie fades, theſe wither like graſſe, but all meete in duſt: The man liues not that ſhall not taſte death: There is a common lot to all, all muſt goe the way of all fleſh; nay! we are now a poſting in the common barke of death, and our life is nothing elſe, but <hi>Iter ad mortem,</hi> a journing towards death; of all thinges death will not bee out-dared,<note place="margin">Theogn.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, impudent death, ſaith the Poet, becauſe hee feares no colours, ſpares none, great nor good.</p>
            <p>Wee therefore ſhould be as impudent, as death to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge that vnto our ſelues, which is denyed vnto all: where are the great Commaunders of the world? where are the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14443:14"/>rulers ouer thouſands, and 10000: The Princes &amp; Potentates of the earth; Are not Death, darkneſſe, and the Graue their lot, the portion of them all? why then in this vniverſall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of death ſhould wee ſue for a diſpenſation for our ſelues or friends? Oh then,<note place="margin">Ferrequam ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem patiuntn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> omnes, nemore cuſet.</note> lift vp your heads yee drooping ſoules, who hang them downe like bulruſhes, &amp; weepe, and will not be comforted, becauſe your Lord, your Maſter, your Honourable friend is not, true he is (not) in a priſon, but in freedome, he is (not) in a ſea, but in the hauen, hee is (not) in the bondage of corruption, but in <hi>the glorious liberty of the ſonnes of God;</hi> he is (not) in his way, but in his Countrey, hee is (not) in hope of Heauen, but in poſſeſſion, &amp; looke how farre Heauen excels earth, goods eternall momentary vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the joyes of the Saints of God, the delights of the ſons of men, ſo much better is his caſe now, he is not then where he was: Oh then, <hi>Pereat contriſtatie ubieſt tanta conſolatie,</hi> forget your ſadneſſe in the midſt of ſuch ioyes, and if theſe Conſolations (becauſe vnſeene) will not dry vp the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of your teares, nor cauſe you to lift vp your heads, then thinke vpon the great Comfort which you ſaw with your owne eyes, <hi>his death, his end,</hi> which was crown'd with the bleſſings of <hi>Peace,</hi> and now at length after much tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, giue me leaue to determine what it is to end or dye in Peace.<note place="margin">What it is to end in Peace. <hi>Pax cogitationis,</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>To end in Peace with <hi>Euthymius,</hi> is to end in <hi>Pace Cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis,</hi> in peace of minde, as it is oppoſed to doubting.</p>
            <p>To end in peace with S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pax ſecuritatis.</note> is to end in <hi>Pace ſecurita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> in peace of ſecurity as it is oppoſed to finall falling.</p>
            <p>To end in peace with <hi>Origen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pax conſcienti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> is to end in <hi>Pace conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> in peace of conſcience as it is oppoſed to deſpairing.</p>
            <p>To end in peace witholde <hi>Iraeneus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pax mortis.</note> is to end in <hi>Pace mortis,</hi> in the peace of death as it is oppoſed to labouring.</p>
            <p>Againe to end in peace, is to end in <hi>Pace Dei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pax Dei. Proxim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Sui.</note> in the peace of God which paſſeth all vnderſtanding (i.) farre beyond mens apprehenſions. To end in peace, is to end in <hi>pace proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi,</hi> in peace with our neighbours (i.) when no out-cryes or
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14443:15"/>exclamations follow vs: And laſtly, to end in peace, is to end in <hi>pace ſui,</hi> in peace with our ſelues, (i.) when no diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions or perturbations of minde moleſt vs. Let happier wits find out, or invent yet more wayes, let them take a Peacefull end or death, which way ſoeuer they will or can, yet a Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full death is ſtill the conſequence of a perfect life: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the next place be pleaſ'd to take ſpeciall notice, what a neceſſary and infallible dependance there is betwixt an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right life,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Note.</hi> Qualis vita, finis us.</note> and a happie and Peacefull death.</p>
            <p>The day neceſſarily followes the riſing of the Sunne, and the night is as neceſſary a conſequence of the falling of the ſame; and the ſame reciprocall dependance there is betwixt. a good life, and a godly death: I haue liu'd perfectly (for ſo the Text argues) That is, I haue had (in ſome meaſure) a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Commaundements of God; I haue liu'd vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly, and kept my ſelfe vnſpotted of the world, what then? why, then I ſhall haue peace at the laſt, and ſo S. <hi>Paul</hi> argues, <hi>I haue fought a good fight, I haue finiſhed my courſe, I haue kept the faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.7.8</note> what then? why, <hi>henceforth there is laide vp for me a crowne of righteouſneſſe:</hi> Oh then, let vs fight a good fight with S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Let vs be followers of him, as hee was of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> that we with him may receiue a Crowne of righteouſneſſe;<note place="margin">The different ends of good and bad liues</note> Let vs keep the faith, and be conſtant vnto death, &amp; then God for his promiſe ſake ſhal giue vs a Crown of Life; Let vs dye vnto ſinne, &amp; wee ſhall liue vnto righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe; Let our bodies be the inſtruments of Gods glory in this World, and they ſhall bee veſſels of honour in the world to come: But if we liue heere without grace, then we muſt looke to dye without hope: if wee ſell our ſelues to worke wickedneſſe euen with greedineſſe, then we muſt expect to dye or end comfortleſſe, voide of that great bleſſing in the Text, <hi>Peace:</hi> I conclude then with <hi>S. Bernards</hi> exhortation, <hi>Si vis in pace mori, ſis ſervus Dei,</hi> hee that will end in peace, muſt ſerue the God of peace.</p>
            <p>And thus <hi>Right Honourable, right worſhipfull, and the reſt heloued in our beſt beloued Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> I haue indeavourd
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14443:15"/>to fulfill the will of the dead, firſt in preaching (according to my ſmall meaſure of knowledge) for the inſtruction of the liuing, &amp; then in ſtirring them vp, (after my plaine manner) by propoſing vnto their higher conſiderations, the patternes of perfect and vpright men, the fitteſt Champions for their imitation. For what man liues better then the vpright man, and what man dyes better then the man that dyes in Peace? which was the accompliſhment of <hi>Abrahams</hi> bleſſing, <hi>Thou ſhalt goe to thy Fathers in Peace:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 5.15.</note> in peace of minde free from doubting, in Peace of ſecurity free from finall falling, in Peace of conſcience free from deſpairing, in peace of death free from labouring, and (which is aboue all) in the <hi>Peace of God which paſſeth all vnderſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Sermon is done for the inſtruction of the liuing, it now beginnes for the honour and commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the dead.</head>
               <p>IT hath beene an Auncient cuſtome in the Church of God for the Fathers to honour the deaths of Gods Saints, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vnto them their iuſt and due praiſes, that the Liuing hearing of their good liues and deathes, may learne to <hi>glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their Father which is in Heauen</hi> for them: Thus was <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> honour'd by <hi>S. Ambroſe;</hi> thus was <hi>Athanaſius</hi> honor'd by <hi>Nazianzene;</hi> thus <hi>Marcella</hi> honour'd by <hi>S. Hierom,</hi> and <hi>Malachy</hi> &amp; <hi>Gerrard</hi> by S. <hi>Bernard.</hi> And yet ſuch hath beene the ſhameful abuſe of this Auncient cuſtome in the Church 06 by the glozing tongues of ſome Paraſites rather then Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, that for vs it will be a matter of great difficultie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſcandall and aſperſion of flattery, to ſpeake of him, the hiſtory of whoſe Life and death cals for a <hi>Liuie</hi> rather then a <hi>Florus,</hi> and for a <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> rather then for a <hi>Phoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> and yet I ſhall remember on what holy ground I ſtand, &amp; in whoſe preſence I ſtand; in the preſence of men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, &amp; which is moſt of all, in the preſence of the Almighty who ſearcheth the hearts &amp; reines. If then in ſuch a preſence I
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14443:16"/>willingly call euill good, &amp; apparell Vice in the Liverie of Vertue, <hi>then let my tongue cleaue to the roof of my mouth:</hi> But If in ſuch a preſence <hi>I ſpeake the truth, I lye not, my conſcience bearing me witneſſe in the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> then let ſuch a preſence witneſſe with mee, that our <hi>Honourable and right Chriſtian Lord</hi> was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, The perfect and vpright man in euery ſenſe and interpretation we haue made of him.</p>
               <p>The perfect man in our firſt ſenſe or interpretation, is the man who hath reſpect to all the Commaundements of God, not allowing himſelfe in the breach of any one of them: And that hee had ſuch a reſpect to the Commaundements of God</p>
               <p>Appeares
<list>
                     <item>1 In his loue to God.</item>
                     <item>2 In his loue to his Neighbour.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>His loue to God appeared firſt by the exerciſe of his devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and religious duties both in publique and priuate, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; euening. Secondly, in the great incouragement &amp; countenance he gaue to the Miniſters of God, by hearing them with a great deale of attention, diligence &amp; piety, by conferring with them with a great deale of devotion &amp; hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, &amp; by his curteous vſage of them, &amp; feeding them like good <hi>Obadiah</hi> alwayes at his owne table with his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. And laſtly, by his building, beautifying and adorning the Houſes of God where he liued: and his exemplar libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie towards the Houſes of Learning, being one of the firſt that gaue his free will offering towards the building of the New Schooles in his Mother Vniverſitie.<note place="margin">Oxon,</note> His loue to his Neighbour appeared in reiceuing the poore. He made his Houſe an Hoſpitall, giuing euery Monday morning, bread, drinke, and money to 15 poore folkes of the neighbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Townes, beſides his charitable Almes at good Times, &amp; his continuall reliefe of them at his gate, he was a good Land-Lord to his Tennants, inſomuch that when one told him hee knew not how to lett his Land, ſetting it at ſo low a rate, his anſwer was, that hee had rather a hundred ſhould gaine by him, then that one ſhould cry out that hee had vndone him.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14443:16"/>Hee was a kinde Maſter to his ſeruants, providing for thoſe that ſerued him faithfully, that they might liue plentifully in their old age, when they were not ſo well able to ſerue. In quieting &amp; ending of differences among the richer, wherein he was happie, that none deſired to appeale from, or went away diſcontented at his ſentence. Diuerſe of his friends tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted him with their whole eſtates, &amp; with the education of their children, and he euer performed the truſt repoſed in him carefully and punctually.</p>
               <p>In our ſecond ſenſe &amp; interpretation, the perfect man was the innocent man, that wrongs no man, oppreſſeth no man, defraudes no man: and then whom hath our perfect man harmed, <hi>whoſe aſſe hath he taken?</hi> as <hi>Samuel's</hi> iuſtification runnes on; nay how many oxen hath he giuen at his gates?</p>
               <p>Conſider Our perfect man in our third ſenſe or interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the ſimple and plaine dealing man, and then with whom hath our perfect man dealt double? His plaineſſe &amp; truth ſought no corners, vſed no aequivocation, no mentall reſervations, as ſtarting holes, (that's a guiſe peculiar to Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Proſelites:) his plaineſſe feared no colours, nor hid it ſelfe vnder the coppy of a fained countenance: no, his rule was the olde &amp; Proverbiall rule, <hi>Qui vadit planè,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 28.18.</note> 
                  <hi>vadit ſanè,</hi> he that walkes plainely, walkes ſafely, and in the end ſhall dye (as our perfect man did) Peaceably.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, take our perfect man in our laſt ſenſe or interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, for that man who is <hi>Integer vitae ſceleriſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> purus,</hi> a man of integrity of heart, vprightneſſe of life and converſation, &amp; then what ſhall we ſay of him who endear oured rather to be good in deed before God, then to be taken onely, or thought to bee good before men? who iudged zeale by truth in's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward affections, deſiring to approue himſelfe to God in the witneſſe of a good conſcience. Now wee may iudge of the Conſcience, of the truth of the trees by the fruites, &amp; a good tree is a good man, which brings forth good fruites; &amp; theſe good fruits are good workes, and then I dare, be bold to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14443:17"/>to the world that our perfect man was a good man becauſe he was fruitfull and rich in good workes.</p>
               <p>And as hee was thus and all theſe waies a perfect man, perfect in regard of innocencie, perfect in regard of harmeleſſe ſimplicity, perfect in regard of integr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and perfect in regard of the miſtery of godlineſſe, and ſauing points of diuinity. So likewiſe, was he a <hi>perfect man</hi> in regard of many arts &amp; ſciences, the hand-maides to that Queene and miſtreſſe: And for his skill in Antiquities, armes, alliances it was ſingular. And for his perfection in Politicall and ſtate affaires, that appeared to the world, as often as hee was called to the great Councell of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, wherein hee laboured for the publique, imploying his beſt indeauours to aduance the good of the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which he euer thought to haue ſo ſtrict a relation, that the good of the one could not ſubſiſt without the good of the other: and it pleaſed God ſo to bleſſe him, that both the King and Kingdome had a good opinion of him. Our late Soueraigne King <hi>Iames</hi> of happy memory thought ſoe well of him that he imployed him in an honourable Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to a forraine Prince, wherein hee ſerued his M<hi rend="sup">•</hi> with a great deale of loyall affection, and was well accepted on both ſides.</p>
               <p>And as he had a full meaſure of knowledge in theſe things, ſo did hee abound in underſtanding and perfection of Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomicall buſineſſe, which firſt appeares vnto the world in the educations of his ſonnes, which was like themſelues ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry honourable in the Vniuerſities, ſchooles of true learning, and ſound religion, whoſe proficiencie there, both honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelues and fitted them for imployment in higher places.</p>
               <p>Secondly, as his wiſdome and vnderſtanding appeared in their educations, ſo it likewiſe was conſpicuous in their honourable marriages: for the ſon of his right hand which ſucceeds him in his chaire of honour. (and long may hee enioy it to Gods glory, the honour of his houſe and country
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14443:17"/>it was his wiſdome to plant and ingraffe him into a familie which is ſecond to none in true honour and nobility;<note place="margin">Earle of Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton. Sir George Fane. Sir Richard Anderſon <hi>Saluſt. ep. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> and for the reſt of his honourable children, hee matched them with families that are euery way very honourable in birth, in blood, in education, in religion: <hi>Quae omnibus ſemper or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natibus ornamento eſt,</hi> which is an ornament to all the reſt, I cannot name theſe religious families without ſome deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and therefore my prayer for them all is, that they may continue long in honour, that they may liue in the ſeruice and feare of god, and dye in his fauour.</p>
               <p>But to returne to their honourable Father and our right noble Lord, who as he wiſely diſpoſ'd of all things concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their <hi>eſſe &amp; bene eſſe</hi> in this life: ſo likewiſe in the ſame meaſure of wiſdome hath he order'd all matters concerning them at his death, bequeathing vnto them his Sauiours Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacie <hi>Peace: my peace I giue vnto you, my peace I leaue with you, that yee may keepe the vnity of ſpirit in the bond of peace.</hi> Thus he liued among them a faire<note n="a" place="margin">Aboue <hi>60.</hi> yeares.</note> age of Peace. Thus hee dyed &amp; left the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in peace. <hi>Sic illi viſum eſt viuere, ſicque mori.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, his vnderſtanding &amp; perfections in Oeconomicall virtues appeares in the well managing of his great eſtate and menes, wherein God bleſſed him aboue his fellowes: It was his great wiſdome to make a carefull frugality the fuell of his continuall hoſpitality, which hath honoured <hi>Spenſers</hi> familie and race in many generations ſucceſſiuely: it was a receiued rule in his Oeconomy, that a man might better keepe a conſtant good houſe, then an vnconſtant vaine pleaſure.</p>
               <p>The laſt thing wherein his vnderſtanding and perfection appeares in theſe matters, is the well ordering and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his houſehold and families: hee kept a great houſe, &amp; yet an orderly, his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts were all of the ſame religion he was of, neither would he keepe any that in ſome good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure did not liue anſwerably to their profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: that as he was in trueth, and not in ſhew onely a perfect man: ſo they like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe might indeauour to attaine that perfection, recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14443:18"/>vnto vs by our Sauiour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5, 48. Bee you pefect as your Father which is in heauen is perfect. And ſoe I leaue the conſideration of him as a perfect man, and intreat you to caſt your thoughts awhile vpon him in the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of an <hi>vpright man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Behold the vpright.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hee was an <hi>vpright</hi> or iuſt man many waies, and yet not the firſt way <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, according to nature, for ſoe no man was euer juſt ſince the fall of <hi>Adam:</hi> but hee was an vpright and iuſt man <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, according to the judgement and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of men, as was <hi>Samuel.</hi> Againe, he was an vpright and juſt man <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.</note> according to purpoſe and true ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour: for with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> he forgot the things which were behind, and reacht forth to the things which are before, and preſſed hard toward the marke for the price of the high cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of God in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, he was an vpright, or iuſt man <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſts righteouſnes, which gaue him an intereſt to that royall blood which is in the perſon of Chriſt, and makes him both to be an heire of the earth, &amp; to haue a title of inheritance vnto heauen.</p>
               <p>Thus ye ſee wee haue found him to bee the vpright man many waies, and diſcouer'd him to bee the perfect man in ſeuerall conſtructions, according to which perfectneſſe and vpright dealing, God for his trueth ſake bleſſed him with a goodly inheritance and pleaſant paradize, wherein in grew in abundance the <hi>Apples of Peace,</hi> which now we are to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the laſt place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The end of that man is peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the end of this perfect and vpright man was (ſoe) crown'd, euen with the bleſſing of peace: of peace which God giues, and of peace which the world giues. This con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in the quiet enjoying of temporall things together with the health of his body for many yeares: That, in the ſweete tranquility of his minde, and in the vnconceaueable joy which now he takes in the contemplation of Gods bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificall viſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:14443:18"/>Againe, his end was in peace, <hi>in pace proximi,</hi> in peace with his neighbour, no outcries, no accurſed acclamations of crueltie and oppreſſion follow his vrne and aſhes. Againe his end was in peace, <hi>in pace ſui</hi> in peace with himſelfe, free from diſtractions of minde, free from conuulſions of body, like a lambe he paſſeth through the gate of mortality into a houſe not made with hands immortall in the heauens.<note place="margin">Mors janu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vitae.</note> The pangs of death to him were ſo eaſie, that he ſeemed to find death rather then to feele it, a bleſſing which <hi>Auguſtus</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten wiſht for <hi>Sibi &amp; ſuis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sueton: in vita ejus.</note> that a glorious life might bee crown'd with a faire and eaſie death. This bleſſing hee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in full meaſure, becauſe hee paſſed away in a preme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditated kind of ſleeping, rather then dying, which is to dye the death of the righteous, for ſo the Hebrewes ſay of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men that they dye, but of the righteous or Saints of God that they fall a ſleepe as <hi>Lorinus</hi> obſerues well on <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niticus.</hi> And yet the honour and comfort of his death ſtood not only in this, that hee went away in a ſleepe gentlie, but principally in this, that as he liued in this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t world, ſo he died godlily, for hauing ſet aſide the trrafficke of this world which paſſeth away, hee trades for an inheritance which fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not reſerued for him in the heauens. Inſomuch that his gratious viſitation towards the end ſeemed farre more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, then in the beginning,<note place="margin">Wormleighton.</note> vvhich vvas clouded vvith ſome more ſadneſſe and deiection of ſpirit, not many daies before his end in peace,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> macrob: in Som. Scip. lib. 10. cap. 11.</note> God put a reſolution into his heart to viſit the place vvhich gaue him the honourable title of a Baron, that his ſoule might bleſſe the poore there alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it's looſing out of the body <hi>Ergaſtulum animae,</hi> the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſoule, and as in fine it happily proued, this journey vvas a ſetting forward towards the kingdome of heauen, for vvithin the ſpace of foure dayes after his arriuall there, the earthly taberuacle of his body vvas<note n="b" place="margin">Octob. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1627.</note> diſſolued, and his ſoule tranſlated from earth to heauen, vvhere our pennes and tongues ſhall let him reſt, onely they craue leaue to make a ſhort hiſtorie of his doings &amp; ſayings, in that ſhort reſpite of life, after his comming to that place.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:14443:19"/>His very firſt act (his priuate acknowledgment of Gods great mercy for his ſafe arriuall there being made) was to ſend for a neighbouring miniſter, (hauing left his houſhold Chaplain at his manſion-houſe to waite on's office with the moſt of his family) whom hee earneſtly deſires to continue with him during his abode ther, morning &amp; euening to pray with him, &amp; to praiſe God for him; that was indeed the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, methode &amp; guiſe of his deuotion, throughout the whole courſe of his ſickenes, like good <hi>Hezekiah</hi> when hee was ſicke, to pray vnto God, and when hee began to amend to praiſe God or giue thanke vnto him.</p>
               <p>The next act of his (which doth preach to the world his religious end) was a gracious meſſage hee ſent to a neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring miniſter, an auncient acquaintance of his, whom notwithſtanding his profeſſion hee godlily exhorts to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare himſelfe, as he did for heauen, intreating him withall to remember him in his daily prayers, promiſing to doe the ſame for him in his continuall deuotions. And whilſt his Catholicke charity and deuotion thus ſpread themſelues on others, was he vnmindfull of his own cauſe? No; he powres forth his complaints and ſupplications for his Gods aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance againſt ſuch paſſions as took moſt aduantage on him in his greateſt weakeneſſe, diſiring withall, his friends and ſeruants, to conſtrue it not as an argument of diſpleaſure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, but rather of his great weakeneſſe when hee ſpoke paſſionately to them in his ſickeneſſe.</p>
               <p>And as his zeale and faith in Chriſt did ſtill increaſe, and the inner man grew ſtronger and ſtronger, ſo his earthly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle or outward man did ſenſibly languiſh &amp; decreaſe; for indeed (as it appear'd by an ocular demonſtration,) the ſtocke of Nature was quite ſpent, his glaſſe was runne, and beeing ripe for heauen, hee was gathered like a ripe apple from the tree, and as he was in his life, <hi>Lucerna ardens &amp; lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens,</hi> a burning and a ſhining candle, ſo it burn'd to the ſnuffe: <hi>Nec extincta eſt tamen ſed ſubmota,</hi> which was not put out but ſet aſide,<note place="margin">In vitâ Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiae.</note> as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpake of his dead friend: his life was a candle which burn'd to the ſnuffe, a ſnuffe which
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14443:19"/>needed not a ſocket to conceale the ſtench, no, at the very laſt, it was as a precious oyntment leauing a ſweet perſume behind it.</p>
               <p>And whileſt that our right Chriſtian Lord was thus dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto the world, but liuing vnto God, it was my great honour (being ſent for before his Chriſtian concluſion,) to be an eye-witneſſe to the vpſhot of his happines.<note place="margin">D. Clayton Reg. Profeſſ. Med: Oxon.</note> It was no ſooner made knowne vnto him by his very learned and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Phyſitian, that I was come (according to my boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den dutie) to doe the office of a miniſter vnto him, but hee ſpeakes affectionately, <hi>let him come in, let him come in with all my heart;</hi> (and ſurely God was in his heart, when his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter was thus the laſt man in his mouth;) and at my admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance into his preſence, my firſt poſture was on the bended knees of my body, which with the bended knees of my ſoule did ſollicite the God of mercy to bow the heauens &amp; to looke downe vpon him with the eyes of mercy; and whil'ſt wee with devoted hearts and hands ſent our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to heauen, not a dew, but a full ſhower of grace and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly benedictions fell downe vpon vs, for behold the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and the heauen of heauens were opened, and the Saintes and Angels ready prepared to receiue his immortall ſoule with all ioyfulneſſe into their manſions of bliſſe and happineſſe. Thus ſhall the man bee bleſt at's death that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth God in's life, hee ſhall bee gathered to his fathers in the words of <hi>Piety,</hi> in the words of <hi>Prayer,</hi> and in the words of <hi>Peace, Peace</hi> of minde, free from doubting; <hi>Peace</hi> of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, free from finall falling; <hi>Peace</hi> of conſcience, free from deſpayring; <hi>Peace</hi> of death, free from labouring; and (which is aboue all) <hi>Peace</hi> of God which paſſeth all vnderſtanding.</p>
               <p>And what now remaines, but that wee deuote our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that as hee reſts in <hi>Peace,</hi> ſo yee may remaine in <hi>Peace,</hi> euen in <hi>Peace</hi> amongſt your ſelues, in <hi>Peace</hi> amongſt your neighbours, in <hi>Peace</hi> amongſt earthly Saintes and heauenly Angels: Laſtly in <hi>Peace</hi> with your God, which paſſeth all mens apprehenſions: Now the God of <hi>Peace</hi> graunt this, &amp; that for his deare ſonnes ſake Chriſt Ieſus, to whom be all honour and glorie now and for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:14443:20"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14443:20"/>
            <lg>
               <l>HOlds yet our ſhatter'd world together ſound?</l>
               <l>Doth it not reele and totter, and looſe ground</l>
               <l>Crumbling towards ruine, whiles deaths fection,</l>
               <l>Sickeneſſe and warre, by troopes, or one by one,</l>
               <l>Cull's out our worthies, which like Ciment ioyn'd</l>
               <l>'Its crazed partes together? when wee finde</l>
               <l>A ſtates or bodies principall decay,</l>
               <l>Such ſymptomes preſage ruine: And wee may</l>
               <l>Too iuſtly feare it, when, in peace and warre</l>
               <l>Death on our beſt and brau'ſt preuailes ſo farre.</l>
               <l>Death might haue ſeiz'd on thouſands elſe beſide</l>
               <l>This noble Lord, and the land gratifide.</l>
               <l>If they had beene our walking magazines;</l>
               <l>It had beene mercy to draw out their mines</l>
               <l>In legacies, and ſome, perhaps, good deede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Or had they beene ſtraite land-lords, who doe feed</l>
               <l>On their poore tenants marrow, and ſtill thinke</l>
               <l>No racke enough, till the ſqueez'd tenants ſhrinke</l>
               <l>To nothing, who with courſe and heartleſſe care</l>
               <l>Pray, and ſo curſe them that bred all their care;</l>
               <l>It had beene mercy, though the ſucceſſour,</l>
               <l>Perhaps abate not ought ſo rack'd vp; for</l>
               <l>All change of torments eaſe: or had they bin</l>
               <l>Some frothy Lords, or featner'd frie, ſtill in</l>
               <l>A tracke of fond and triuiall expence</l>
               <l>Of coine and time, and of their wit and ſence;</l>
               <l>Theſe, and ten thouſand ſuch might well bee ſpar'd</l>
               <l>Nor would the ſtate, by their death, be impair'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:14443:21"/>
               <l>But when a Noble Lord breathes out his laſt,</l>
               <l>The ſtate ſuſtaines an Earth-quake, and is caſt,</l>
               <l>As to that limme into a Lethargie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lords are like ſtarres, which guilt from heauens bright eye</l>
               <l>Reflects i'ts ſplendour, and their influence</l>
               <l>On the inferiour globe, from their orbes, whence</l>
               <l>They diuerſly diſpenſe it. And when Death</l>
               <l>Bereaues a mortall ſtarre of his laſt breath,</l>
               <l>The ſunne wants ſo much demonſtration</l>
               <l>Of light, and ſo much influence is gone</l>
               <l>Which clear'd the world. And he that could relate</l>
               <l>What influence both on the Church and State</l>
               <l>Flow'd from this Noble Lord, what cheerefull light</l>
               <l>Hee ſhed abroad, to doe his Countrey right,</l>
               <l>Whoſe good hee tender'd with more neere reſpect</l>
               <l>Then ought that on his priuate did reflect.</l>
               <l>What warmth his beames of goodneſſe did impart</l>
               <l>To the diſtreſſ'd, ſad both in face and heart,</l>
               <l>What an vnwearied, large, and open hand</l>
               <l>Hee ſtretch'd out to the poore, and how his land</l>
               <l>Was by their backes and bellies bleſt, while they</l>
               <l>Like rounds in <hi>Iacobs</hi> Ladder, ſate each day</l>
               <l>In troupes about his hoſpitable gate,</l>
               <l>Whence laden with his almes, early and late</l>
               <l>They haſted to their coates, and timely fed</l>
               <l>Their bedrid mates, and infants with his bread,</l>
               <l>What bounteous entertainment, and how free</l>
               <l>And hearty welcome, euery gueſt might ſee</l>
               <l>Both in his face and houſe, which for reſort</l>
               <l>And entertainment was a ſtanding court</l>
               <l>Where euery honeſt man, though ne're ſo plaine</l>
               <l>As welcome was, as if a ſcarlet traine</l>
               <l>Or ſilken ſaile had vſherd him, and hee</l>
               <l>Might freely ſpeake his mind, and neuer bee</l>
               <l>Thought ſawcy, and commaund a finer man</l>
               <l>To fill him wine, who ne'er would frowne &amp; ſcan</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14443:21"/>The cups or paines, but would his beſt afford</l>
               <l>To the mean'ſt gueſt, enioyn'd ſo by his Lord.</l>
               <l>How iuſt he was in all his actions,</l>
               <l>How free from racking or oppreſſions,</l>
               <l>Hovv farre from cauſing any poore mans grone,</l>
               <l>Hovv prone to heare and right the meaneſt one,</l>
               <l>What large revvards and meanes of liuelyhood</l>
               <l>His ſeruant had from him, vvho vnderſtood</l>
               <l>And lou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the ſervice; And how firme a friend</l>
               <l>He was, how ready Goodnes to defend,</l>
               <l>What progeny he left, how train'd and bred</l>
               <l>To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ue and ſtand the Common-wealth in ſtead</l>
               <l>In any courſe it ſtear'd; And how he ſhone</l>
               <l>With Piety and true Devotion,</l>
               <l>Which op'd and cloſ'd his each day. He that could</l>
               <l>In fitting termes relate theſe as he ſhould</l>
               <l>To Truthes honour and His, and take in all</l>
               <l>Which in this large Circumference muſt fall,</l>
               <l>Might write the tru'ſt and ſaddeſt Elegye</l>
               <l>Tbat e're appear'd vnto a blubber'd eye;</l>
               <l>But the ſad Countreyes face, and poore mans crye</l>
               <l>Supply a liuing laſting Elegye,</l>
               <l>By whom, their Patron, and their Patriot,</l>
               <l>Though no verſe were, will neuer be forgot.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>YOu are deceiu'd, Great <hi>Spencer</hi> is not dead;</l>
               <l>Hee's dead, who when hee's gone is periſhed.</l>
               <l>Hee's dead of whom there's nothing doth remaine,</l>
               <l>Which may remembrance of his life retaine.</l>
               <l>Hee's worſe then dead, whoſe liſe had ſo much blame,</l>
               <l>That after him there nought remaines but ſhame,</l>
               <l>But glorious great good <hi>Spencer</hi> neuer dyes;</l>
               <l>Who liues well heere, ſure liues aboue the skyes.</l>
               <l>Of gracious <hi>Spencer</hi> there is nothing loſt,</l>
               <l>But his ſweet preſence, which hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tely coſt</l>
               <l>So many a heauy ſigh, and teare, and groane,</l>
               <l>Whiles he in white, leaues vs in ſable moane.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14443:22"/>His ſweet embalmed aſhes in their vrne,</l>
               <l>Doe breed a glorious Phoenix in the turne,</l>
               <l>Of Nature into glory, when the mould</l>
               <l>Of the new framed World ſhall ne're grow ould.</l>
               <l>Not any power created can vnmake</l>
               <l>One graine of duſt: O then lett's comfort take:</l>
               <l>Reſt thou ſweet Bride, and for thy Brige-groome ſtay,</l>
               <l>Both ſhall be crown'd at the great wedding Day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Great <hi>Spencer</hi> liue in thy Poſterity,</l>
               <l>Thy fame on earth, Thou in Eternity.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>THe Sunne did ſet, a ſhowre of teares did fall,</l>
               <l>A night of ſorrow did o're-ſpread vs all.</l>
               <l>The cloud did darken all <hi>Northampton</hi> pale,</l>
               <l>And thence did ouer-ſhaddow all the vale,</l>
               <l>And mountaines of <hi>Great Brittaine:</hi> teares that fell</l>
               <l>From Engliſh eyes his worth, our ſorrowes tell.</l>
               <l>But bleſt be Heauen, a glorious Sunne appeares,</l>
               <l>Which cleares the Aire, and all the Countrey cheeres.</l>
               <l>From <hi>Englands</hi> Center <hi>Spencers</hi> happy ſeate,</l>
               <l>His wiſdome giueth light, his goodneſſe heate.</l>
               <l>The Church, the Muſes, all the Country find</l>
               <l>In him that good, which in his Father ſhin'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shine long bright Sunne, our loſſes to repaire,</l>
               <l>And may thy Houſe ne're want ſo good an Heire.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <head>An Epitaph.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>HEre lyes S. <hi>Mathewes</hi> bleſſed man, <note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> if ere</l>
               <l>Within Earths bovvels he intombed vvere.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Humble</hi> in <hi>Minde.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 3. &amp; 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Mourning</hi> theſe euill dayes.</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Courteous</hi> and humbly <hi>Meeke</hi> in all his vvayes.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iuſtice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>and right he made his meate and drinke.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 7.</note> His <hi>Mercy</hi> claſp't the poore vvhen like to ſinke.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A man of Peace.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 9. &amp; 8</note> 
                  <hi>Of heart and conſcience pure.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And for his <hi>Worth</hi> by ſome he <hi>ſuffer'd</hi> ſure.</l>
               <l>'Twas his perfection cauſ'd our griefe; <note place="margin">Verſ. 10.</note> His death</l>
               <l>A heap of vertues, which did ſtop his breath.</l>
               <l>His goodnes rob'd vs of him; had Gods will</l>
               <l>Been like to moſt, we had enioy'd him ſtill.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14443:22"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>AVlicus, Vrbanus, Muſarum docta caterva;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Totaque</hi> Spencerum <hi>terra Britanna dolet.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non dedignatur Coelum ſibi ſumere veſtem</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Atratam, &amp; multas ſolvitur in lachrymas.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(<hi>Ille pius, iuſtuſquefuit, patriaeque fidelis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Muſis patronus, pauperibuſque pater.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Clare vale</hi> Spencere, <hi>vale reverende Patrone,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et longùm ſplendens vivat imago tui.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VNthankfull vvorld, vvhich ſtill imput'ſt the crimes.</l>
               <l>Of thine ovvne folly to theſe latter times,</l>
               <l>As if all things vvere vvorſe, and Natures ſtrength</l>
               <l>VVere vvaſted ſo, that ſhee muſt ſinke at length.</l>
               <l>If learned <hi>Hackwell</hi> haue not chaung'd this thought,</l>
               <l>And prou'd 'tis not the time, but thou art nought.</l>
               <l>See an Heroicke, vvho I dare preſage,</l>
               <l>Our ſonnes vvill ſay, liu'd in a golden age;</l>
               <l>Men vvere but good at Beſt, nor could they more</l>
               <l>Then vvhat vvas iuſt. Thoſe vvhom vve moſt adore</l>
               <l>Did liue at large. Had Mine and Thine beene knovvne</l>
               <l>In <hi>Saturnes</hi> dayes, men vvould haue held their ovvne.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spencer</hi> vvas great, good, rich, and nobly free,</l>
               <l>To ſhevv 'twa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not his vvealth vvas Lord, but hee.</l>
               <l>His vvealth did cheriſh vvorth, for vvhere he ſpy'd</l>
               <l>But ſparkes of infant goodnes, there he try'd</l>
               <l>To raiſe a flame, and vvould not let it dye,</l>
               <l>But ſtill reviv'd it vvith a freſh ſupplye.</l>
               <l>Young as I am and vveake, not vvorth the care</l>
               <l>Of ſuch an honour'd Lord, I had my ſhare:</l>
               <l>And humbly craue a roome to moane his death</l>
               <l>VVho heartned me and gaue my ſtudies breath.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
